{
  "reference_number": "9557",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission proposed under the Bill should be given the task of plotting precisely how New Zealand hits its net\n zero emissions target."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The climate does not distinguish between different greenhouse gases: carbon dioxide (CO2) from cars, methane (CH4) from\n\n livestock, or nitrous oxide (N2O) from fertiliser and manure. They all warm the planet."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We have a history of global leadership: we were the first country to give women the vote and the first to become nuclear free. It is\n time to take another giant step towards climate justice globally."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "In its strongest warning yet about the dangers of climate change, the UN's Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) said in\n its Fifth Assessment Report that only \"rapid and far-reaching\" changes to the world's economy would prevent temperatures from\n\n rising 1.5degC above pre-industrial times. Beyond 1.5degC of warming, the risk of climate change impacts on ecosystems moves\n from moderate to high. The circumstances will only worsen given the facts of how Climate has changed drastically over the past\n\n decade. Net Zero is the only option."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "As long as it aligns with the Paris Agreement."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However, these considerations should be looked at with a long term lense on rather than a short three year long political party lense.\nThis is for the benefit of Pacific and other developing countries, those who have contributed least to the causes of climate change\n\nare typically the most vulnerable to its impacts and have the least resources to respond."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The bill must include a requirement to produce annual reports about New Zealand’s international climate change contributions in\norder to ensure that the Pacific countries get the support they need and can plan to adapt to their changing environment. Include\n\nPacific Climate scientist in this process, they are our whanau and we should be working with them on this process. Transparency with\nthe Bill to promote public engagement and political accountability. The Zero Carbon Bill should aim to support the most vulnerable\n\npeople in the Pacific."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission should be full of experts, therefore it would be make sense that they defined the number of units.\n\nThe only thing would be to check any conflict of interest with any members dependent on business and property ownership."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Desirable attributes - not required. I also believe there should be a few Pacific voices on the commissions, for example from Kiribati or\npeople who have worked in the development sector specialising in Climate Science in developing countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I believe this function could sit within the Climate Change Commission. New Zealand has demonstrated global leadership with our\ncommitment to stopping oil and gas exploration – now let us continue that moral leadership and include transparency in what and\n\nhow we support climate change efforts abroad."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Large changes to the climate need to involve a stronger look at the way in which NZers do business here and across the globe.\n\nThere is social inequity here in NZ and with our Pacific whanau, we should be supporting equitable sustainable climate action, which\n(unfortunately for only a small percent) will mean that they will need to pay more because they have significantly more. I hope this\nconsideration is a big part of the actions that will come out of this act? I also hope that NZ ETS and the adaptation reporting power\n\nchecks closely for ways that people may get around this system, because many NZers are not fond of change and may look for quick\nfixes that do not support the extreme changes that need to be made to mitigate climate change (and maybe adapt, if possible)."
    }
  ]
}
